<?xml version='1.0' ?><!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V5.0//EN" "../lib/docbook-5.0.dtd" >

<chapter xml:id="TransformationWizard">
	<title>Transformation Wizard</title>
	<section>
		<title>Opening the wizard</title>
		<para>
			The transformation wizard provides a UI for applying and testing
			transformations. An action for opening the wizard is provided in the
			context of Rules, TransformationUnits, TransformationSystems and
			henshin-files. Inside the henshin-editor the popup menu provides an
			action "Apply with Henshin" as shown in
			<xref linkend="fig_WizardMenuAction"></xref>
			. The popup menu of the Package Explorer lists the action in the
			Henshin submenu.
			<figure xml:id="fig_WizardMenuAction">
				<title>Wizard menu entry</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata align="center" fileref="img/WizardMenuAction.png"></imagedata>
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
		</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Wizard Elements</title>
		<para>
			The wizard's interface is made of a single page containing
			several sections that allow to configure the different aspects of a
			transformation's application. The following illustrates the UI
			elements in detail. 	
		</para>
		<figure xml:id="fig_Wizard">
			<title>Wizard</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata align="center" fileref="img/Wizard_.png"></imagedata>
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
		<orderedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>Select the Rule or TransformationUnit that shall be executed.
					This selector is only enabled if the wizard is opened in the
					context of a TransforamtionSystem or a henshin-file. Otherwise the
					Rule or TransforamtionUnit for which the wizard was opened will be
					fixed.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Select the resource you wish to transform. Only the first
					content element of the resource will be used as the graph.The
					element is inserted as root. This means that the graph will consist
					of the element itself and all transitively contained objects.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					Set values for the parameters of the chosen unit. Since all
					values
					are entered as strings, it is necessary to also select a
					type. The
					given string-value is parsed as the defined type, which is then
					passed to the transformation.
					<figure xml:id="fig_WizardParameterTypes">
						<title>Selecting a parameter's type</title>
						<mediaobject>
							<imageobject>
								<imagedata align="center" fileref="img/Wizard_ParameterTypes.png"></imagedata>
							</imageobject>
						</mediaobject>
					</figure>
					There are two types which do not allow a value to be entered:
					<itemizedlist>
						<listitem>
							<para>
								The type
								<emphasis>Ignore</emphasis>
								prevent a parameter from being initialized. This option must be
								used for parameters that pre-match a node in the LHS.
							</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para>
								The type
								<emphasis>Null</emphasis>
								initializes a parameter with null. If the parameter is used as
								an attribute value in the LHS, the attribute value of a
								match
								must be null. In case the parameter defines a prematch-node,
								setting the Null-type will prevent the unit from being
								applicable.
							</para>
						</listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>This allows to see a preview of the transformation. The
					transformation will be applied to a copy of the selected model. The
					differences are detected and visualized using EMF Compare.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Applies the transformation to the selected model and writes
					the result back to the resource. This action is encapsulated as an
					undoable operation using the Eclipse Command Framework. Note that
					this does not place an undoable command on the EMF CommandStack
					inside the editor. To undo a transformation you have to focus the
					Package Explorer. This will switch the context of the edit-menu to
					the platform's operation history.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Cancel closes the dialog without applying the transformation.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					This flag indicates whether the settings shall be saved even if the
					transformation was not applied. The current settings are
					automatically saved when the dialog is closed via the
					<emphasis>Transform</emphasis>
					button. If you are in the process of developing a transformation,
					usually you will only preview your transformation's effects without
					applying them to the selected model. To avoid having to select a
					model and entering parameter values each time, those settings may
					are saved if the
					<emphasis>Save Cfg on Cancel</emphasis>
					is checked, even if the dialog is canceled.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					Provides access to
					<emphasis>this document</emphasis>
					.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</orderedlist>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Transformation Preview</title>
		<para>
			EMF Compare is used to preview a transformation's effect on a given
			model. As shown in
			<xref linkend="fig_WizardPreview"></xref>
			, a transformed copy is compared to the original model. To inspect
			the changes of the parameter values, the preview window provides a
			second page, that lists the parameters of the applied unit together
			with their initial values and their values after the transformation
			was applied.

			<xref linkend="fig_WizardPreviewParameters"></xref>
			shows a changed parameter value that is used to externalize an object
			that was matched by a node named "package". Note that here the type
			of the parameters has to be
			<emphasis>Ignore</emphasis>
			. This guarantees that the parameter does not affect the
			match-finding. The parameter will hold a reference to the object
			matched by the "package"-node.
			<figure xml:id="fig_WizardPreview">
				<title>Wizard Preview</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata align="center" fileref="img/WizardPreview.png"></imagedata>
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			<figure xml:id="fig_WizardPreviewParameters">
				<title>Wizard Parameter Preview</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata align="center" fileref="img/WizardPreviewParameters.png"></imagedata>
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
		</para>
	</section>


</chapter>